Guide to the Tyler Ingolia collection of Popstitutes videotapes, 1988-1997.
Ingolia, Tyler collection of Popstitutes videotapes
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Tyler Ingolia collection of Popstitutes videotapes, 1988-1997.
7830
Ingolia, Tyler,
14 VHS cassette tapes.
Video cassettes.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Original videocassette recordings of performances by the Popstitutes. Performers who appear in the videos include Michael Collins, Brad Kellogg, Alvin Orloff; cabaret performer, writer, and transgender activist Justin Vivian Bond; transwoman cabaret singers Veronica Klaus and Bambi Lake; composer and filmmaker Jack Curtis Dubowsky; pop novelty act the Del Rubio Triplets; punk performers and writers Jennifer Blowdryer and Danielle Willis; Drew Daniel of the experimental electronic music duo Matmos; painter and queercore performer Jerome Caja; avant-garde drag performer The Steve Lady (Steven Price); and Fudgie Frottage (Lu Read), co-founder of the San Francisco Drag King Contest. None of the videos have been published or posted online.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
The Popstitutes were an influential San Francisco queer performance group and punk band founded in 1986 by Michael Collins ("Diet Popstitute"), Brad Kellogg ("Bad Popstitute"), and Alvin Orloff ("Remix von Popstitute"). Tyler Ingolia performed as a dancer and extra with the Popstitutes, and appeared regularly in sketches presented at Klubstitute, the itinerant weekly queer club night hosted by the Popstitutes in the first half of the 1990s.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Original videocassette recordings of performances by the Popstitutes. Performers who appear in the videos include Michael Collins, Brad Kellogg, Alvin Orloff; cabaret performer, writer, and transgender activist Justin Vivian Bond; transwoman cabaret singers Veronica Klaus and Bambi Lake; composer and filmmaker Jack Curtis Dubowsky; pop novelty act the Del Rubio Triplets; punk performers and writers Jennifer Blowdryer and Danielle Willis; Drew Daniel of the experimental electronic music duo Matmos; painter and queercore performer Jerome Caja; avant-garde drag performer The Steve Lady (Steven Price); and Fudgie Frottage (Lu Read), co-founder of the San Francisco Drag King Contest. None of the videos have been published or posted online.
The collection also includes an unreleased documentary about the Lavender Tortoise, a combination of bus tour and performance art that brought a coachload of drag queens and queer punks to Los Angeles and Disneyland in 1991. Several Klubstitute regulars participated in the trip. Also included is a video of an early show at Trannyshack, a week drag cabaret and queer dance club hosted by Heklina from 1996 to 2008 at The Stud in San Francisco. A number of performers who had made their names at Klubstitute went on to appear at Trannyshack.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Ingolia, Tyler,; Blowdryer, Jennifer.; Bond, Justin.; Caja, Jerome, 1958-1995.; Collins, Michael, 1958-1995.; Daniel, Drew.; Dubowsky, Jack Curtis.; Frottage, Fudgie.; Kellogg, Bradley.; Klaus, Veronica.; Lake, Bambi, 1950-; Orloff, Alvin, 1961-; Steve Lady, 1971-2008.; Willis, Danielle.; Del Rubio Triplets (Novelty act); Klubstitute (Nightclub); Popstitutes (Musical group); Trannyshack (Nightclub); Lavender Tortoise (Tour)
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Use Restrictions:
Due to the fragility and potential degradation of moving image and sound recordings, viewing and listening is limited to items that have been digitized. If an item is in another media format, you may request to have the item digitized for access. Information on ordering access copies may be found on our Reproductions and Permissions page.
NOTES
Collecting program: Human Sexuality Collection.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Popstitutes
Series II. Klubstitute
Series III. Miscellaneous
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Popstitutes
  - The Popstitutes, 1989; V-8990 (Box 1)
    Easter at the DNA Lounge (San Francisco). This event was produced and hosted by Lu Read (aka Fudgie Frottage). The Popstitutes headlining with the Del Rubio Triplets, along with Phillip R. Ford and others. Video by Rapa (last name unknown).
  - "The Mugging", plus Southern Exposure Shower Scene/Bed Scene; The Popstitutes, ca. 1988; V-8991 (Box 1)
    First performance at Southern Exposure (San Francisco). Most likely promotional videos created by Bradley Kellog, Michael Collins and Alvin Orloff.
  - Smutfest (1 and 2?), Popstitutes performance, 1990; V-8992 (Box 1)
    DNA Loundge (San Francisco). This was the first of Jennifer Blowdryer's Smutfests in San Francisco. Headlined by The Popstitutes, with special guest dancer Jerome Caja. Huge line-up of other performers, including Danielle Willis, Lily Braindrop, Phillip R. Ford.
    Smutfest 2 was the second of Jennifer Blowdryer's Smutfests, held at the DNA Lounge (August 1990). The Popstitutes were again the headliner. Line-up of performers included Bambi Lake, Veronica Klaus, Danielle Willis and many others. Both shows videotaped by Sister Aqua Divina.
  - The Popstitutes w/ Blatz., 1991; V-8993 (Box 1)
    Performance at 924 Gilman Street Project (Berkeley). Videotaped by Kevin Gladstone for his cable-access queer TV Show, Striaght Talk TV.
- Series II. Klubstitute
  - James T & the Kirkettes. Star Trek Video, ca. 1991; V-8994 (Box 1)
    Short video directed and filmed by Michael Macintosh. A Star Trek parody with characters from the original series and the "Next Generation" TV show. Featuring Leigh Crow as Kirk, Zeon Kircher as Uhura, Tyler Ingolia as Counselor Deanna Troi, Johnny Kat as Yeoman Rand. Liegh performs "Lucy In The Sky with Diamonds" to William Shatner's recorded version.
  - New Wave Video 2000: Missionary Man/Somebody Told Me/Copy (Me)/Star Wars Docs, ca. 1994; V-8995 (Box 1)
    Excerpt from "New Wave Video 2000 #5" of Tyler Ingolia covering Eurythmics with a live musical accompaniment by Sean Kennedy.
  - Soap Box Derby/Video 2000 New Wave, Nite at Klubstitute/RuPaul [illegible]/Surf Show, 1993; V-8996 (Box 1)
    Klubstitute at a warehouse space (name unknown). Hosted by Diet Popstitute and cohosted by David Hawkins. A go-cart race around the block outside the club, featuring go-carts created the previous week by various Klubstitute performers, activists and artists, such as Justin Bond and Robbie D.
    Also the first "New Wave Video 2000," parody of the Southern California new wave dance party music video shoe called MV3. Hosted by Deena Davenport. Live and lip-synched performances by many Klubstitute luminaries: Justin Bond, Robbie D. tyler Ingolia, Seanetta, Mark Menke, Sean Kennedy and others. Djs Alvin Orloff (Popstitutes) and Drew Daniels (Matmos). Videotaped by Sean Kennedy.
  - Deena Davenport's New Wave Video 2000, 1994; V-8997 (Box 1)
    Might be New Wave Video 2000 II, Klubstitute at The Stud (San Francisco) as videotaped from different vantage points by David Jude Thomas. There may be brief interviews, etc. DJ Robbie D.
  - New Wave Video 2000, Vol. I, II, II. Klubstitute., 1993-1995; V-8998 (Box 1)
    An edited compilation of the shows also listed as II and III in the next two tapes. Video taped by Sean Kennedy and David Jude Thomas.
  - Deena Davenport's New Wave Video 2000 II & III/Klubstitute/The Stud. Sean's Version, 1994; V-8999 (Box 1)
    Klubstitute at The Stud (San Francisco). Show: New Wave Video 2000 II and III, a parody of the Southern California new wave dance party music video show called MV3. Hosted by Deena Davenport. Live and lip-synched performances by many Klubstitute luminaries: Justin Bond, Robbie D. tyler Ingolia, Seanetta, Mark Menke, Sean Kennedy and others. Djs Alvin Orloff (Popstitutes) and Drew Daniels (Matmos). Videotaped by Sean Kennedy.
  - Deena Davenport's New Wave Video 2000 III. Klubstitute. Original copy, 1994; V-9000 (Box 1)
    Third New Wave Video 2000 show. Probably Klubstitute at The Stud or at what used to be The Oasis (both in San Francisco). DJs Alvin Orloff (Popstitutes) and Drew Daniels (Matmos).
  - New Wave Video 2000 #5, 1995; V-9001 (Box 1)
    Klubstitute at The Cat Club (San Francisco). Fifth New Wave Video 2000 show. This is one of the better shows, most of the performances were live, with a live band. Performances by Sean Kennedy, Tyler Ingolia, Jack Curtis Dubowsky and classical ensemble, many more. Videotaped by Sean Kennedy.
- Series III. Miscellaneous
  - The Lavender Tortoise, 1991; V-9002 (Box 1)
    Documentary of Greg Taylor's "Lavender Tortoise" queer tour for Los Angeles and Disneyland. Directed by Ken Woodard.
  - Bowie, T. Shack. Witch Hazel & Model Stuff., 1997; V-9003 (Box 1)
    First tribute to David Bowie at Trannyshack (San Francisco). Hosted by Heklina, co-hosted by The Steve Lady (Steven Price) as Iman-Ch-Chi and a plethora of early Trannyshack performers. DJ Robbie D.